Register of the José Ovidio Puente papers
Hoover Institution Archives
José Ovidio Puente papers
1928-2010
2001C110
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet
Correspondence, writings, serial issues, clippings, photographs, and miscellany, relating to Frente Sandinista de Liberación Nacional guerrillas in Nicaragua. Includes writings and letters by the Sandinista leader Carlos Fonseca.
Puente, José Ovidio.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Mexican leftist activist.
Scope and Content of Collection
The José Ovidio Puente papers contain materials that largely relate to Nicaragua and, in particular, to the Sandinista movement that overthrew the dictatorship of Anastasio Somoza in 1979. Through his association with a number of Sandinista activists, Ovidio Puente came into possession of documents pertaining to the guerrilla war waged by the Sandinistas against Somoza. Of special note within the collection are a number of unpublished writings by Carlos Fonseca Amador, one of the original founders of the Frente Sandinista de Liberación (FSLN). Among these is the manuscript of a general history of Nicaragua written while the author was a political prisoner. The collection also includes correspondence and a large number of scanned photographs.
In addition to Ovidio Puente's own correspondence, the collection contains a separate series of correspondence among other individuals. There are also some additional writings, including a lengthy manuscript by Virgilio Godoy Gutiérrez on the 1920s guerrilla movement of Augusto Sandino, a revolutionary from whom the FSLN drew inspiration as well as its name.
Fonseca Amador, Carlos.; Frente Sandinista de Liberación Nacional.; Guerrillas--Nicaragua.
- Correspondence, 1962-1982
  - Unidentified, 1965-1975 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Bravo, Jaime, 1979 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Hernandez, Graciela "Chelita", 1973-1980 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Ortega, Humberto, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Paye Puentes, Maye, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Reyes, Osacar D., 1964 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Rivas de Torres, Marta, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Torres, Edelberto, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Torres Rivas, Myrna E., 1977 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Quiñones, Julian, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Wheelock, Ricardo, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 11)
- Other correspondence (neither to nor from José Ovidio Puente), 1960-1979
  - Unidentified, 1960-1975
    - General, 1960-1975 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Maria Cristina (surname unknown), 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - Maria L. (surname unknown), 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1: 14)
    - Marina (surname unknown), 1970 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Borge, Tomás, 1979 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Guerrero Santiago, Noel, 1962 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Martínez O., Eulogio, 1964 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - O'Cerda, Daniel Simeon, 1973 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Ortega, Humberto, 1965 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Pavletich, Esteban, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Sánchez, Abelardo, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Solis Arce, Miriam de, 1963 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Sosa A., Jacinto, 1972 (Box-folder 1: 24)
- Carlos Fonseca Amador file, 1964-1975
  - Cards from medical laboratory, 1965 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Clippings, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Letter from Lupe Salinas, 1971 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Writings, 1964-1975
    - "Ensayo sobre la situacíon economica y política nacionales", undated (Box-folder 1: 28)
    - "Mensaje al pueblo de Nicaragua desde las carceles de la aviación a la juventud", 1964 (Box-folder 1: 29)
    - Reading notes, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 1: 30)
    - History of Nicaragua, 1970 (Box-folder 1: 31)
    - "Programa Sandinista", 1970 (Box-folder 1: 32)
    - "Nicaragua, la lucha es contra cuarenta años de tiranía", 1975 (Box-folder 1: 33)
- Writings by others, 1928-1975
  - Unidentified, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 34)
  - Godoy Gutiérrez, Virgilio, 1975 (Box-folder 33: 5)
  - Mena Solózarno, Luís, 1944 (Box-folder 1: 36)
  - Pavletich, Esteban, 1928-1975 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Sandino, Augusto C., 1978 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Varallanos, José, 1928 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- Communiqué and leaflet, 1975 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Subject file, 1963-1980
  - Blanco, Hugo, 1968 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Escobar Pérez, José Benito, 1964 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Frente Sandinista de Liberación Nacional, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Nicaragua, 1963-1968 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Spadafora, Hugo, 1980 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Torres, Edelberto, 1977 (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Miscellany, 1964-1979
  - Fragments of interviews, 1978 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - List of conference participants, 1979 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - List of Sandinista militants, 1965 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Mathematical calculations, 1965 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Membership card, 1964 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Receipts, 1965-1970 (Box-folder 2: 16)
- Photographs, 1948-2010
  - Prints, 1956-1970
    - Tomás Borge, 1965 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - Francisco Buitrago, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 18)
    - Carlos Fonseca Amador, 1958 (Box-folder 2: 19)
    - Heriberto Rodríguez Marín, 1963-1964 (Box-folder 2: 20)
    - Miskito activist, 1962 (Box-folder 2: 21)
    - Unidentified, 1956-1970
      - 1956-1957 (Box-folder 2: 22)
      - 1959-1960 (Box-folder 2: 23)
      - 1963 (Box-folder 2: 24)
      - 1970 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Digital scans of photographs returned to José Ovidio Puente, 1948-2010
    Access
    Digital use copies are available in the reading room.
    - List of scans, 2010 (Box-folder 2: 26)
    - DVD discs containing digital scans, 1948-1993
      - 1948-1993 (Box-folder 2: 27)
      - 1950-1959 (Box-folder 2: 28-30)
      - 1960-1969 (Box-folder 2: 31)
      - 1970-1979 (Box-folder 2: 32-33)
      - Undated (Box-folder 2: 34-42)
    - CD-Rom containing reference images, 1948-1993 (Box-folder 2: 43)
- Incremental materials (Box 3)